<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>DayakDaily</title>
	<atom:link href="https://dayakdaily.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://dayakdaily.com</link>
	<description>We Choose Sarawak</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 07:26:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DayakDaily-logo-new.png?fit=32%2C32&#038;ssl=1</url>
	<title>DayakDaily</title>
	<link>https://dayakdaily.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">137258927</site>	<item>
		<title>PETRONAS-PETROS commercial settlement talks ongoing, outcome expected by early 2026</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/petronas-petros-commercial-settlement-talks-ongoing-outcome-expected-by-early-2026/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Editor KB]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 07:26:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[BEYOND SARAWAK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2026 Sarawak Budget Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amir Hamzah Azizan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[commercial settlement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fadillah Yusof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Petronas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Petros]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313739</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Karen Bong KUCHING, Dec 16: Negotiations between Petroliam Nasional Berhad (PETRONAS) and Petroleum Sarawak Berhad (PETROS) on a commercial settlement are progressing, with formal correspondence already underway and an outcome expected as early as next year. Deputy Prime Minister Datuk Amar Fadillah Yusof said both the Prime Minister Datuk Seri Anwar Ibrahim and Sarawak [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Karen Bong</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: Negotiations between Petroliam Nasional Berhad (PETRONAS) and Petroleum Sarawak Berhad (PETROS) on a commercial settlement are progressing, with formal correspondence already underway and an outcome expected as early as next year. </p>
<p>Deputy Prime Minister Datuk Amar Fadillah Yusof said both the Prime Minister Datuk Seri Anwar Ibrahim and Sarawak Premier Datuk Patinggi Tan Sri Abang Johari Tun Openg had agreed that a commercial settlement was the most practical and constructive approach for resolving issues between PETRONAS and PETROS.</p>
<p>“If you go along the interpretation of the laws, there will be a longer and more complex settlement because you have to go through court processes and so on. At the end of the day, it may not be win-win, but lose-lose for all parties,” he said at the 2026 Sarawak Budget Conference at the Borneo Convention Centre Kuching (BCCK) today. </p>
<p>Instead, Fadillah explained that both national and State leaders had agreed for PETRONAS and PETROS to sit down together and identify areas where they could collaborate, stressing that cooperation would ultimately benefit not only the companies involved, but also the nation and the wider business community.</p>
<p>“This win-win approach is what we have agreed on. There is already correspondence between PETRONAS and PETROS, and hopefully by early next year we should be able to know the result from the negotiation, which is currently still ongoing,” he said.</p>
<p>However when met by members of the press later, he cautioned that if the two parties were unable to reach an agreement, legal avenues could still be pursued, though he expressed hope that this could be avoided.</p>
<p>Speaking during a forum session titled Exploring Sarawak’s Future: The Fourth Madani Budget and 13MP as Catalyst for Growth, Minister of Finance II Senator Datuk Seri Amir Hamzah Azizan echoed the importance of cooperation, describing the oil and gas sector as a critical pillar of Malaysia’s and Sarawak’s economy.</p>
<p>He noted that PETRONAS had invested an estimated RM290 billion over the years to develop the oil and gas sector, while Sarawak had received close to RM80 billion in returns through royalties, dividends and spin-offs, including equity participation in Bintulu Port.</p>
<p>“The key was that this worked because there was an attitude that we must work together. From exploration to development, export and downstream manufacturing, the entire supply chain must be secured. That has proven to be the winning formula for Malaysia,” he said.</p>
<p>Amir said this principle had also been anchored in the understanding reached between the federal and Sarawak governments, urging both sides to focus on practical solutions rather than allowing tensions to escalate.</p>
<p>“The worst thing that can happen when there is friction is that people lose trust in our system. When they lose trust, they don’t invest and that’s a lose-lose position that we really don’t want to go down,” he said.</p>
<p>He added that both sides had also agreed in principle to make more gas available for domestic utilisation in Sarawak, strengthening the State’s infrastructure and its ability to attract industries and enhance economic complexity.</p>
<p>“This engine must continue moving forward. If it is interrupted, our aspirations to raise economic complexity will also be affected,” he said, expressing optimism that “cooler heads will prevail” given the understanding reached at the highest leadership level between the Prime Minister and the Sarawak Premier. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313739</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Deputy minister proposes workshop to preserve Iban ‘baju kuas’, eyes Borneo Cultures Museum showcase</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/deputy-minister-proposes-workshop-to-preserve-iban-baju-kuas-eyes-borneo-cultures-museum-showcase/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Editor DL]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 07:16:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[baju kuas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Snowdan Lawan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[traditional attire]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313734</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By DayakDaily Team KUCHING, Dec 16: Efforts will be made to ensure that the legacy of the ‘baju kuas’ craftsmanship is displayed at the Borneo Cultures Museum (BCM), says Deputy Minister of Tourism, Creative Industry, and Performing Arts, Datuk Snowdan Lawan. In a press release, he said that arrangements will be made to interview the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By DayakDaily Team</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: Efforts will be made to ensure that the legacy of the ‘baju kuas’ craftsmanship is displayed at the Borneo Cultures Museum (BCM), says Deputy Minister of Tourism, Creative Industry, and Performing Arts, Datuk Snowdan Lawan.</p>
<p>In a press release, he said that arrangements will be made to interview the curator of the baju kuas, Julia James, when officiating at the closing ceremony of a baju kuas workshop by Julia at the Centre for Technology Excellence Sarawak (CENTEXS) in Santubong on Sunday (Dec 14).</p>
<p>The traditional baju kuas is a distinctive garment worn by the women of the Iban Balau community, who mostly reside in the Simanggang, Banting, Undop, Lingga, and Pantu areas.</p>
<p>It is a meticulously crafted garment made mostly from black coloured cloth and woven and skilfully knitted by fine coloured threads, beads, and other accessories. Originally worn during festivals, weddings, and traditional events, it has since become a family heirloom.</p>
<figure id="attachment_313736" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-313736" style="width: 800px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img data-recalc-dims="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-313736" src="https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/WhatsApp-Image-2025-12-16-at-14.38.24_4077db76.jpg?resize=696%2C928&#038;ssl=1" alt="" width="696" height="928" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/WhatsApp-Image-2025-12-16-at-14.38.24_4077db76.jpg?w=800&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/WhatsApp-Image-2025-12-16-at-14.38.24_4077db76.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/WhatsApp-Image-2025-12-16-at-14.38.24_4077db76.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/WhatsApp-Image-2025-12-16-at-14.38.24_4077db76.jpg?resize=315%2C420&amp;ssl=1 315w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/WhatsApp-Image-2025-12-16-at-14.38.24_4077db76.jpg?resize=696%2C928&amp;ssl=1 696w" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-313736" class="wp-caption-text">A display of the baju kuas worn by the women of the Iban Balau community.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Having seen for himself how the baju kuas is crafted, and noting that his grandparents were originally from Banting, Snowdan said the making of the traditional attire is of particular interest to him.</p>
<p>He suggested that a workshop be initiated to promote and pass on the craft, especially to the younger generation, to prevent the legacy from fading into extinction.</p>
<p>“Julia James and her family took this challenge, while the ministry lends the necessary financial support and CENTEXs provides the premises platform. This is a commendable effort,” he remarked.</p>
<p>Snowdan also urged them to add value to their creativity so that their products can be monetised and have commercial value. Ultimately, he said, this would enable the craft to become a sustainable business undertaking.</p>
<p>At present, depending on the design and materials used, a piece of baju kuas can fetch between RM1,500 and RM3,000, which he described as quite lucrative by industry standards.</p>
<p>During the event, Snowdan handed over certificates to 24 participants, made up of the Iban, Malay, Bidayuh, and Orang Ulu communities.</p>
<p>Also present was Association of Wives of Ministers and Deputy Ministers of Sarawak (Sabati) exco member Datin Melinda Claudia Bucking. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313734</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sarawak Metro awards RM58 mil contract to Linde EOX to upgrade, relocate KUTS hydrogen plant</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/sarawak-metro-awards-rm58-mil-contract-to-linde-eox-to-upgrade-relocate-kuts-hydrogen-plant/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Editor DL]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 05:02:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kuching Urban Transit System (KUTS)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linde EOX Sdn Bhd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sarawak Metro]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By DayakDaily Team KUCHING, Dec 16: The Kuching Urban Transportation System (KUTS) Project has reached another major milestone with Sarawak Metro Sdn Bhd awarding a contract to Linde EOX Sdn Bhd for the relocation and upgrading of Sarawak Energy’s hydrogen production plant and refuelling station. According to a press release, the hydrogen plant will be [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By DayakDaily Team</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: The Kuching Urban Transportation System (KUTS) Project has reached another major milestone with Sarawak Metro Sdn Bhd awarding a contract to Linde EOX Sdn Bhd for the relocation and upgrading of Sarawak Energy’s hydrogen production plant and refuelling station.</p>
<p>According to a press release, the hydrogen plant will be relocated from Bintawa to the Autonomous Rapid Transit (ART) Depot in Rembus, Kota Samarahan.</p>
<p>On Monday (Dec 15), Sarawak Metro received the signed Letter of Acceptance (LOA) from Linde EOX for the relocation and upgrading of the said hydrogen production and refuelling station, under Phase 1 of the hydrogen production strategy for the KUTS Project.</p>
<p>Sarawak Metro chief executive officer Ts Mazli Mustaffa was on hand to receive the signed LOA from Linde EOX managing director, Hoo Peih Yoke, at Sarawak Metro’s corporate office here.</p>
<p>The design and build contract is valued at RM58 million and is expected to be completed in time for the start of operations of the KUTS project by the fourth quarter of 2026.</p>
<p>Once fully upgraded, the plant will be able to produce approximately one tonne of green hydrogen.</p>
<p>On hand to witness the handing over of the signed LOA were Ministry of Transport Sarawak permanent secretary Datu Wong Hee Sieng and a representative from Sarawak Financial Secretary’s Office, Mohamad Kamil Asyraf Mohamad Samuri. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313731</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Anglican Church to host Association of Churches Joint Christmas Service 2025 on Dec 18</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/anglican-church-to-host-association-of-churches-joint-christmas-service-2025-on-dec-18/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amanda L]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 04:19:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Association of Churches in Sarawak (ACS)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christmas service]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313721</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Amanda L KUCHING, Dec 16: The Anglican Church will host this year’s Association of Churches in Sarawak (ACS) Joint Christmas Service on Thursday (Dec 18) at the Christian Ecumenical Worship Centre here, bringing together Christians from different denominations to celebrate Christmas in unity. Speaking at a press conference here today, ACS secretary-general Elder Ambrose [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Amanda L</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: The Anglican Church will host this year’s Association of Churches in Sarawak (ACS) Joint Christmas Service on Thursday (Dec 18) at the Christian Ecumenical Worship Centre here, bringing together Christians from different denominations to celebrate Christmas in unity.</p>
<p>Speaking at a press conference here today, ACS secretary-general Elder Ambrose Linang said the service, themed &#8216;Emmanuel: God with Us&#8217;, will reflect Sarawak’s diversity, with prayers and scripture readings conducted in English, Bahasa Malaysia, Mandarin, Iban and Bidayuh Biatah.</p>
<p>“The programme will feature a carol procession led by the Boys’ Brigade Drums and Bagpipes, followed by candle lighting by heads of churches and a children’s presentation titled ‘God with Us’ by the Sunday Schools of St Thomas’ Cathedral and St Basil Church,” he said.</p>
<p>Congregational carols, he added, will be led by a combined choir of 85 members from ACS member churches, conducted by Evelyn Lim, and accompanied by an eight-member string orchestra from Universiti Malaysia Sarawak (UNIMAS) and two sape players.</p>
<p>The opening prayer will be led by Rev Timothy Ling, while the benediction by the heads of churches will be led by Archbishop Dato Simon Poh.</p>
<p>“Christian elected representatives, heads of departments and community leaders have been invited to attend the service, together with friends from other faiths including Buddhist, Hindu, Sikh and Baha&#8217;i communities,” he said, noting that ACS continues to promote the spirit of togetherness, unity and religious tolerance through activities carried out across Sarawak. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313721</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>PM tells JKR to expedite S’wak Cancer Centre project to be tendered in Q1 2026, operational before 2031</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/pm-tells-jkr-to-expedite-swak-cancer-centre-project-to-be-tendered-in-q1-2026-operational-before-2031/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Editor DL]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 04:14:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sarawak Cancer Centre]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sim Kui Hian]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313726</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By DayakDaily Team KUCHING, Dec 16: Prime Minister Datuk Seri Anwar Ibrahim has instructed the Public Works Department (JKR) to expedite the Sarawak Cancer Centre (SCC) project, which is slated for tender in the first quarter of 2026 and targeted to be completed and operational before 2031. In a Facebook post, Deputy Premier Datuk Amar [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By DayakDaily Team</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: Prime Minister Datuk Seri Anwar Ibrahim has instructed the Public Works Department (JKR) to expedite the <a href="https://dayakdaily.com/sarawak-cancer-centre-construction-to-start-by-2026-with-rm1-52-bln-preliminary-estimate-cost/">Sarawak Cancer Centre (SCC) project</a>, which is slated for tender in the first quarter of 2026 and targeted to be completed and operational before 2031.</p>
<p>In a Facebook post, Deputy Premier Datuk Amar Dr Sim Kui Hian said this followed a special project monitoring meeting chaired by the prime minister at Putrajaya on Monday (Dec 15), where the SCC was among the four projects presented.</p>
<p>Dr Sim, who is also the Minister for Public Health, Housing, and Local Government, added that the groundbreaking for the project is expected to take place in the third quarter of 2026.</p>
<p>“Cancer patients in Sarawak need state-of-the-art facilities so that our medical specialists in SGH (Sarawak General Hospital) can do more,” he said.</p>
<p>He said that the SCC will not only be the largest and only full-fledged dedicated cancer centre in Malaysia, but it will also form an important component of the <a href="https://dayakdaily.com/sarawak-cancer-centre-to-anchor-samarahan-health-metropolis-as-msias-larged-dedicated-facility/">Sarawak Health Metropolis in Samarahan</a>.</p>
<p>At the same time, he also touched on the challenges faced in retaining medical subspecialists, as their services are sought after worldwide.</p>
<p>“When it comes to subspecialist hospitals, it is important that we have not only world-class infrastructure but also world-class doctors and nurses.</p>
<p>“Similarly, I always told everyone, if any of the doctors or medical specialists are not up to standard in Malaysia, we should not pass them even though we are in severe shortage of doctors,” he said, adding there are no shortcuts when it comes to human lives.</p>
<p>The centre will feature 310 beds within a gross floor area of 154,498.26 square metres, with a total cost of RM1.5 billion. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313726</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>SUPP sec-gen: If UEC recognition has constitutional issues, debate amendment in Parliament</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/supp-sec-gen-if-uec-recognition-has-constitutional-issues-debate-amendment-in-parliament/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Editor DL]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 03:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[BEYOND SARAWAK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sebastian Ting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Unified Examination Certificate (UEC)]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313724</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By DayakDaily Team KUCHING, Dec 16: If the federal government maintains that the recognition of the Unified Examination Certificate (UEC) involves constitutional issues, then the responsible and democratic approach would be to propose a constitutional amendment through Parliament, allowing the matter to be debated openly and transparently and decided through a parliamentary vote. In a [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By DayakDaily Team</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: If the federal government maintains that the recognition of the Unified Examination Certificate (UEC) involves constitutional issues, then the responsible and democratic approach would be to propose a constitutional amendment through Parliament, allowing the matter to be debated openly and transparently and decided through a parliamentary vote.</p>
<p>In a statement, Sarawak United Peoples’ Party (SUPP) secretary-general Datuk Sebastian Ting said that UEC recognition is not a political manoeuvre, but a major education issue that directly affects the future of the next generation.</p>
<p>“Education is of fundamental importance to our children and students. The government has a responsibility to provide the best possible educational opportunities and a conducive learning environment, which naturally includes language education. Education policies must be forward-looking and genuinely focused on preparing children for future global competition, rather than being confined by outdated thinking,” he said.</p>
<p>He said that the Chinese language is rapidly growing its importance in international trade, technological cooperation and regional engagement, emerging as another important international language similar to English.</p>
<p>Ting noted that in recent years, many Middle Eastern and Muslim-majority countries have formally incorporated the Chinese language into their national education systems.</p>
<p>“Saudi Arabia has introduced Chinese language programmes in selected schools, while countries such as Iran, Egypt, the United Arab Emirates, Tunisia, and Pakistan have also begun offering Chinese language classes at the school level.</p>
<p>“At the same time, Saudi education authorities have introduced various incentives to encourage the learning of Chinese, including study and exchange programmes in China. Under Saudi Vision 2030, Chinese language skills are explicitly identified as an important competency in sectors such as tourism and entertainment,” he said.</p>
<p>He said this demonstrates that Chinese is no longer a niche language but is steadily becoming an important international language.</p>
<p>“Education policies should be centred on the interests of children, not driven by political considerations. Ignoring the importance of language skills and multicultural education will undermine our children’s ability to compete with their peers from other countries, which would be an irresponsible approach to the nation’s future,” he said.</p>
<p>Ting also highlighted that students enrolled in independent Chinese secondary schools today also include indigenous students, allowing them access to an additional language and to acquire broader skills that create more opportunities and possibilities for their future.</p>
<p>“SUPP will continue to firmly uphold multicultural education and fair access to educational opportunities and urges the federal government to re-examine the UEC issue with a more open, pragmatic and forward-looking approach, truly acting in the best interests of the nation and future generations,” he said. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313724</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Balai Ringin clinic gets much-needed medical equipment under PETRONAS-SABATI Christmas drive</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/balai-ringin-clinic-gets-much-needed-medical-equipment-under-petronas-sabati-christmas-drive/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Editor KB]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 01:46:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Association of Wives of Ministers and Assistant Ministers Sarawak (Sabati)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Balai Ringin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Snowdan Lawan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yayasan Petronas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313718</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By DayakDaily Team KUCHING, Dec 16: The Balai Ringin Health Clinic has received badly needed medical equipment under the Memacu Kehidupan Krismas Balai Ringin programme, a strategic collaboration between Yayasan PETRONAS and Association of Wives of Ministers and Assistant Ministers of Sarawak (SABATI), aimed at improving healthcare services and easing the burden on the local [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By DayakDaily Team</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 16: The Balai Ringin Health Clinic has received badly needed medical equipment under the Memacu Kehidupan Krismas Balai Ringin programme, a strategic collaboration between Yayasan PETRONAS and Association of Wives of Ministers and Assistant Ministers of Sarawak (SABATI), aimed at improving healthcare services and easing the burden on the local community.</p>
<p>Balai Ringin assemblyman Datuk Snowdan Lawan said the initiative has brought meaningful and positive impact to the people, particularly through the upgrading of healthcare facilities and the distribution of Christmas food baskets to eligible recipients.</p>
<p>“I applaud this programme because the strategic collaboration between PETRONAS and SABATI has truly touched the lives of the people and made a real difference to their daily lives,” he said when officiating at the programme and the handing over of basic medical equipment at his service centre here on Friday (Dec 12).</p>
<p>On behalf of the people of Balai Ringin, Snowdan expressed his gratitude as the health clinic received various essential medical equipment, including counter waiting chairs, hospital beds, wheelchairs, an infusion pump, a heavy-duty nebuliser and other necessary items.</p>
<p>“These new equipment are not only badly needed but are also meant to replace old and obsolete ones. With these improvements, the clinic will be able to deliver better healthcare services to the community,” he said.</p>
<p>In conjunction with the upcoming Christmas celebration, a total of 204 households also received Christmas food baskets sponsored by Yayasan PETRONAS, which Snowdan said would help ease the financial burden of eligible families. The recipients were identified based on the e-Kasih registration data.</p>
<p>He added that the collaboration is in line with Sarawak’s Post-Covid-19 Development Strategy (PCDS) 2030, which emphasises holistic and inclusive development to improve the quality of life of the people.</p>
<p>During the event, Snowdan, who is also Deputy Minister for Tourism, Creative Industry and Performing Arts, also presented certificates of appointment to 11 village headmen under the jurisdiction of the Balai Ringin sub-district.</p>
<p>He advised them to work closely with government agencies and provide full cooperation in the implementation of ongoing and future development projects in their respective areas.<br />
Meanwhile, five churches in the Balai Ringin constituency received Unit for Other Religions (Unifor) assistance amounting to RM1.005 million from the Gabungan Parti Sarawak (GPS) government. The funds are intended to help churches upgrade their places of worship as well as to support a mission school.</p>
<p>Earlier, Snowdan paid a walkabout visit to the Balai Ringin health clinic to observe its facilities and services and expressed his satisfaction upon seeing a newly delivered, sophisticated ambulance vehicle at the clinic.</p>
<p>Among those present were Snowdan’s wife Datin Melinda Claudia Bucking Lawan and five other SABATI exco members as well as PETRONAS Sarawak general manager Norazibah Md Rabu. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313718</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Premiership: Not for Glamour and Glory</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/premiership-not-for-glamour-and-glory/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marlynda Meraw]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Datuk Patinggi Tan Sri Abang Johari Tun Openg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MA63]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[premiership]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313671</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Lian Cheng “When we have this status, it doesn’t mean that we want to be proud. People say it’s because of glorification. It’s not glorification. It’s because of what we have signed before during the formation of Malaysia (referring to the Malaysia Agreement 1963), and it must be recognised.” Abang Johari (February 19, 2022) [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Lian Cheng</p>
<p><em>“When we have this status, it doesn’t mean that we want to be proud. People say it’s because of glorification. It’s not glorification. It’s because of what we have signed before during the formation of Malaysia (referring to the Malaysia Agreement 1963), and it must be recognised.” <a href="https://dayakdaily.com/abang-jo-premier-title-not-for-me-but-for-sarawak/">Abang Johari (February 19, 2022) </a></em></p>
<p>MARCH 1, 2022, will echo through time as a defining moment in Sarawak’s history. On this day, the State witnessed a monumental shift as the title of its head of government was elevated from ‘Chief Minister’ to ‘Premier’. This change was more than mere symbolism, it stood as a powerful declaration of Sarawak’s enduring resolve to reclaim the State rights that have, over time, been gradually eroded.</p>
<p>By adopting the title ‘Premier’, Sarawak sent a clear and resounding message: the State remains steadfast in its efforts to restore the rights and privileges enshrined within the Malaysia Agreement 1963 (MA63).</p>
<p><strong>Higher Titles, Greater Responsibilities</strong></p>
<p>On February 15, 2022, the Minister of Tourism, Creative Industry, and Performing Arts Dato Sri Abdul Karim Rahman Hamzah, tabled the Constitution of the Sarawak (Amendment) Bill 2022 to change the designation of ‘Chief Minister of Sarawak’ to ‘Premier of Sarawak’. Abdul Karim, who also holds the portfolio of Youth and Sports Minister, explained that the Bill aligned with the Constitution (Amendment) Act 2022 [Act A1642], which had come into effect on February 11, 2022, following the recent amendments of the Federal Constitution to restore the MA63.</p>
<p>He emphasised that Sarawak’s special status necessitated a distinct representation, setting it apart from other states in the Federation of Malaysia. As such, the designation of ‘Chief Minister’ was no longer appropriate and needed to be re-styled as ‘Premier’. The amendment also brought with it a broader shift in nomenclature within Sarawak’s executive ranks. The ‘assistant minister’ title was formally replaced with ‘deputy minister’. As a result, all 27 ‘assistant ministers’ would be officially redesignated as ‘deputy ministers’, should the Bill be passed and put into effect.</p>
<p>Abdul Karim explained that the change was necessary given the increasing scope of duties these deputy ministers would hold and exercise. It is only fitting that their titles better reflect the substance of their roles. The Sarawak Legislative Assembly passed the Bill with a two-thirds majority, supported by 67 members of the august house while six opposed it after a second round of voting by show of hands before Speaker Tan Sri Mohammad Asfia Awang Nassar.</p>
<p>Five days later on February 19, 2022, Abang Johari who at that point still held the title ‘Chief Minister of Sarawak’, explained that the new title of ‘Premier’ was not for just one person, but for the whole of Sarawak. He reiterated that the move to redesignate ‘Chief Minister’ to ‘Premier’ was to reflect Sarawak’s different status from the other states in the Federation of Malaysia.</p>
<p>“It’s not glorification. It’s because of what we had signed before, during the formation of Malaysia, and it must be recognised,” he said during the Federation of the Division Chinese Association Sarawak’s Unity Night Year 2022 at a local hotel on February 19, 2022, in reference to the MA63 which states that Sarawak is an equal partner to Peninsular Malaysia in the formation of the Federation of Malaysia.</p>
<p><strong>The Fight Must Go On </strong></p>
<p>Abang Johari further pointed out that although he would one day retire, the pursuit of restoring Sarawak’s rights must continue.</p>
<p>“I won’t be the Chief Minister or Premier for a long time. One day, I’ll have to say ‘thank you’ and ‘goodbye’.</p>
<p>“Then, the country must be in harmony and progressive. And it is our vision to transform Sarawak as an economic hub, not only for Malaysia, but for the region,” said Abang Johari.</p>
<p>Following its passing, the Bill was gazetted on March 1, 2022, from which date the title ‘Chief Minister of Sarawak’ was officially re-designated as the ‘Premier of Sarawak’.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>The content featured here is an excerpt from the book “Rise of Sarawak: Abang Johari’s Era of Transformation&#8221;, published by Sage Salute Sdn Bhd. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313671</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Young pâtissier Tan’s Crémo stirred yoghurt is the next sweet hit for Kuching dessert lovers</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/young-patissier-tans-cremo-stirred-yoghurt-is-the-next-sweet-hit-for-kuching-dessert-lovers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marlynda Meraw]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human interest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313711</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Wilfred Pilo KUCHING, Dec 15: At just 24, pâtissier Jacky Tan has embarked on a sweet venture that he hopes will capture the hearts and taste buds of dessert enthusiasts across Kuching. Driven by a bold ambition to satisfy local sweet-toothed customers, Tan has developed his own version of stirred yoghurt under the name [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Wilfred Pilo</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 15: At just 24, pâtissier Jacky Tan has embarked on a sweet venture that he hopes will capture the hearts and taste buds of dessert enthusiasts across Kuching.</p>
<p>Driven by a bold ambition to satisfy local sweet-toothed customers, Tan has developed his own version of stirred yoghurt under the name Crémo, offering what he describes as a creamy, rich and exquisite dessert experience.</p>
<p>His culinary journey began at 19, when he set out to create delicious food that would keep locals coming back for more.</p>
<p>That path took him to Japan, where he immersed himself in the country&#8217;s renowned cuisine.</p>
<p>“I landed in Japan a few years back and worked there to learn their cuisine. I really appreciated and mastered it,” Tan told DayakDaily when met at a vendor event in the city.</p>
<p>Despite briefly exploring the corporate world with a nine-to-five banking job to understand the financial sector, Tan&#8217;s heart remained firmly rooted in the culinary arts.</p>
<p>&#8220;My true passion is still in culinary arts and providing the best to satisfy customers&#8217; palates,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p>Armed with culinary research and experimentation, Tan spent months developing yoghurt flavours he believed would resonate with customers. The result was Crémo; an exquisite stirred yoghurt dessert that he crafted to be creamy, mild and original.</p>
<p>What sets his product apart is its clean ingredient list.</p>
<p>“I made this irresistible yoghurt without preservatives, added sugar, pork or lard, so everyone could have a taste of my creations,” he enthused.</p>
<p>Standing firmly beside Tan in this venture is his 23-year-old girlfriend, Yeo Kai Xun, who actively supports his vision of bringing Crémo to customers&#8217; plates across the city.</p>
<p>Yeo said she believes in Tan’s philosophy and energy, ensuring their genuine flavours reach those seeking a satisfying dessert experience.</p>
<p>She noted that Tan comes from a family well-known in the culinary world for their bakkwa (dried pork), and that he shares the same passion for his own creations.</p>
<p>So far, Tan has created four flavours: mango, passion fruit, strawberry and mixed berries, all of which have been instant hits with customers since the couple opened their stall to the public.</p>
<figure id="attachment_313712" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-313712" style="width: 898px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" class="wp-image-313712 size-full" src="https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Kch-dd151225-wp-cremo.p2.jpeg?resize=696%2C392&#038;ssl=1" alt="" width="696" height="392" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Kch-dd151225-wp-cremo.p2.jpeg?w=898&amp;ssl=1 898w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Kch-dd151225-wp-cremo.p2.jpeg?resize=300%2C169&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Kch-dd151225-wp-cremo.p2.jpeg?resize=768%2C433&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Kch-dd151225-wp-cremo.p2.jpeg?resize=745%2C420&amp;ssl=1 745w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Kch-dd151225-wp-cremo.p2.jpeg?resize=696%2C392&amp;ssl=1 696w" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-313712" class="wp-caption-text">Varieties of stirred yoghurt in a chiller by Crémo.</figcaption></figure>
<p>&#8220;We are proud that his products have an audience, and this is a big moment for us at this vendor market since we have had these products for about half a year,&#8221; Yeo said.</p>
<p>She describes both herself and Tan as bold young entrepreneurs eager to expand into a bigger playing field. While their entrepreneurial journey is still in its infancy, she believes they have already achieved significant milestones towards their dream.</p>
<p>&#8220;We know in our hearts that we want to work hard and ensure that our stirred yoghurt is competitive and loved. And I will be there for him,&#8221; she said with a chuckle.</p>
<p>The couple harbours hopes that Crémo will one day become a household name for dessert in Sarawak and beyond.</p>
<p>Beyond yoghurt, they also offer bagel crisps and creamy cupcakes designed to woo customers with diverse tastes.</p>
<p>For now, they can be found at The Podium Street Mall during the Woo Woo Whimsy event. Those interested in trying Crémo&#8217;s offerings can reach them at 011-25023015 or follow them on Instagram at @cremo_kch. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313711</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Batik Air launches daily Kota Kinabalu-Kuching flights</title>
		<link>https://dayakdaily.com/batik-air-launches-daily-kota-kinabalu-kuching-flights/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marlynda Meraw]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:21:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[BEYOND SARAWAK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEATURED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LOCAL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Batik Air]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Datuk Dr Jerip Susil]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dayakdaily.com/?p=313707</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Amanda L KUCHING, Dec 15: Batik Air has commenced daily direct flights between Kota Kinabalu and Kuching, enhancing travel convenience and strengthening air connectivity between Sabah and Sarawak. Deputy Minister for Transport Sarawak (Aviation and Road) Datuk Dr Jerip Susil said the new service reflects Sarawak’s commitment to improving inter-state air links in collaboration [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Amanda L</p>
<p>KUCHING, Dec 15: Batik Air has commenced daily direct flights between Kota Kinabalu and Kuching, enhancing travel convenience and strengthening air connectivity between Sabah and Sarawak.</p>
<p>Deputy Minister for Transport Sarawak (Aviation and Road) Datuk Dr Jerip Susil said the new service reflects Sarawak’s commitment to improving inter-state air links in collaboration with federal agencies and airline operators.</p>
<p>Under the daily schedule, flight OD1682 arrives in Kuching from Kota Kinabalu at 6.30pm, while the return flight OD1683 departs Kuching at 7.20pm.</p>
<p>“Batik Air also operates four additional flights weekly on Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Sundays. OD1684 arrives at 9.45am and OD1685 departs at 10.35am, bringing total weekly frequency to 11 flights,” said Jerip at a press conference following the inaugural direct flight at Kuching International Airport (KIA) today.</p>
<figure id="attachment_313709" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-313709" style="width: 1000px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-313709" src="https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=696%2C522&#038;ssl=1" alt="" width="696" height="522" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?w=1000&amp;ssl=1 1000w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=560%2C420&amp;ssl=1 560w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=80%2C60&amp;ssl=1 80w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=696%2C522&amp;ssl=1 696w, https://i0.wp.com/dayakdaily.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9341.jpg?resize=265%2C198&amp;ssl=1 265w" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-313709" class="wp-caption-text">Batik Air flight from Kota Kinabalu arriving at Kuching International Airport (KIA) on Dec 15, 2025, was greeted with a water salute.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Dr Jerip described the Kota Kinabalu–Kuching route as a strategic milestone that is expected to stimulate trade, tourism, logistics and services, while also supporting small and medium enterprises (SMEs) in both states.</p>
<p>He noted the encouraging response to the inaugural service, which recorded 120 arriving passengers and 120 departing passengers, reflecting strong demand and market confidence in the route.</p>
<p>“With Visit Malaysia Year 2026 approaching, enhanced Sabah–Sarawak air connectivity is timely. It will encourage multi-destination travel within Sarawak through direct and indirect links via Kota Kinabalu,” he added. — DayakDaily</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">313707</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
